Inventory of the Beverly Papers 1796-1834
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Beverly Papers, 1796-1834.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.2 B46
73 items.
Chiefly letters to Robert Beverley, Jr. of "Blandfield," Essex County, Virginia and Georgetown, D.C., from his brother-in-law Brett Randolph of Culpeper County, Virginia and his nephew Richard Randolph, Jr.
Robert Beverley,; Lucy Beverley Randolph,; Richard Randolph,; Brett Randolph,; John Howe Peyton,; William Augustine Washington.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 73 items, 5/01/1927.
Biographical/Historical Information
The following biographical sketch is not meant to be exhaustive but merely a brief genealogical sketch of the main contributors/creators of this collection. A more definitive source on the Beverly genealogy can be found in the book, The Beverley family of Virginia; descendants of Major Robert Beverley, 1641-1687, and allied families, by John McGill.
Robert Beverley (d.1800) was born in "Blandfield" Virginia. He received his education in England and was elected to the state legislature in 1780 but never took his seat. He married Maria Carter (1745-1817) of "Sabine Hall" Richmond County, Virginia. Together they had the following sixteen children: William Beverley (1763-1823), Maria Beverley (1764-1824), Robert Beverley (1766-1767), Robert Beverley (1769-1843), Lucy Beverley (1771-1854), Burton Beverley (1772-1781), Carter Beverley (b. 1774), Byrd Beverley (b. 1775), James Mills Beverley (1776-1779), Anna Munford Beverley (1778-1830), Munford Beverley (1779-1820), Peter Randolph Beverley (b. 1780), Evelyn Byrd Beverley (1782-1836), McKenzie Beverley (b. 1783), Jane Bradshaw Beverley (1784-1814), Harriet Beverley (1786-1829).
The fourth child of Robert Beverley (d.1800), Robert Beverley (1769-1843), like his father, was also educated in England. He married Jane Tayloe (1774-1816) and lived in "Blandfield." Together they had the following six children: William Bradshaw Beverley (1791-1866), Maria Beverley (d. 1822), Rebecca Tayloe Beverley (d. 1822), James Bradshaw Beverley (b. 1797), Jane Bradshaw Beverley (1805-1822), and Roberta Beverley. Three of the children contracted typhoid fever and died in 1822 upon a visit home to "Blandfield" to visit their parents.
The fifth child of Robert Beverley (d.1800), Lucy Beverley (1771-1854) married Brett Randolph (1766-1828) of "Curles Neck," Henrico County, Virginia in 1789. They had the following eleven children: a son Randolph (1790-1790), Capt. Edward Brett Randolph (1792-1848), Dr. Robert Carter Randolph (1793-1854), Richard Randolph (1795-1885), Victor Moreau Randolph (1797-1876), John Thomson Randolph (1800-1819), Benjamin Franklin Randolph (1801-1802), Benjamin Franklin Randolph (1803-1890), Ryland Randolph (1805-1853), Theoderick Bland Randolph (b. 1807), and Ann Maria Randolph (1811-1845).
Scope and Content Information
Chiefly letters written to Robert Beverley (1769-1843) of "Blandfield," Essex County, Virginia and Georgetown, D.C. from his sister Lucy (Beverley) Randolph, her husband Brett Randolph and their son Richard Randolph, Jr. (1795-1885). The letters concern slaves given to Lucy Beverley Randolph and her children by her father Robert Beverley (d. 1800), and held in trust by her brother Robert Beverley, some of which were sold to pay debts incurred by her husband.
Also includes letters concerning the lawsuit Beverley v. Pickett, Scott et al. in chancery; the will of John Randolph of Roanoke; and letters, 1830, from John H. Peyton and William Augustine Washington concerning litigation over claims to George Washington's Kanawha lands; and William Byrd's lottery.
Arrangement
Organization
This inventory is organized into one series of letters. All other material not included these series is listed separately.
Arrangement
Series 1, containing letters, is arranged chronologically by date with those items lacking a date located at the end of the series.
Additional Related Material
Bibliography
For additional genealogy and biographical material see John McGill's book entitled The Beverley Family of Virginia. The College of William and Mary, Swem Library has two copies of this book in seperate locations. One is located in the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department and the other can be found in the Swem Library Stacks. Collection Number: CS71 B5772 1956
McGill, John, 1880-1951. The Beverley family of Virginia; descendants of Major Robert Beverley, 1641-1687, and allied families. Columbia, S.C.: R.L. Bryan Co., 1956. Pages 535, 549, and 571.
Index Terms
Persons:
Beverley, Robert, d. 1800.; Beverley, Robert, 1769- 1843.; Byrd, William, 1728-1777.; Randolph, Lucy Beverley, 1771-1854.; Randolph, Richard, 1795-1885.; Randolph, Brett, 1766-1828.; Peyton, John Howe, 1778-1847.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; Washington, William Augustine, fl. 1809-1830.
Subjects:
Slavery-- Virginia--History.; Lotteries--United States.
Components List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1796-1834. (Folder 1-2)
  - Letters, 1796-1799., 11 items. (Folder 1)
    - Lucy Randolph, at Sandy Ford, to her brother, Robert Beverley, Jr., at Blandfield, Essex County, 13 April 1796. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, at Curles, [Henrico County], to Robert Beverley, Jr., at Sans Souci, [Culpeper County], 6 June 1796. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, Prince Edward [County], to Robert Beverley, Jr., at Sans Souci, Culpeper County, 26 June 1796. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, Prince Edward [County], to Robert Beverley, Jr., Culpeper County, 10 August 1796. (Folder 1)
    - Lucy Randolph, at Sandy Ford, to Robert Beverley, Jr., at Sans Souci, Culpeper [County], 28 October 1796. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, Jr., to Robert Beverley, Jr., at Sans Souci, Culpeper [County], 4 December 1796. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, Prince Edward [County], to Robert Beverley, Jr., at Sans Souci, Culpeper County, 14 January 1797. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, Jr., Prince Edward [County], to Robert Beverley, Jr., Culpeper County, 19 August 1797. (Folder 1)
    - Lucy Randolph, at Curles, [Henrico County], to Robert Beverley, Jr., at Sans Souci, Culpeper [County], 29 March 1798. (Folder 1)
    - Lucy Randolph, at Curles, [Henrico County], to Robert Beverley, Jr., 6 May 1799. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, Jr., at Richmond, to Robert Beverley, Jr., Culpeper County, 24 September 1799. (Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1800-1809., 23 items. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 10 May 1800. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, [Essex County], 28 July 1800. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 19 September 1800. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, [Culpeper County], to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 7 January 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 7 March 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 18 March 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 3 June 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, [Culpeper County], to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Essex County, 17 August 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 2 September 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, Jr., Culpeper County, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 8 September 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, [Culpeper County], to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 25 October 1801. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, [Essex County], 14 July 1802. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Mansfield, 2 February 1803. (Folder 1)
      This letter includes an account of Robert Beverley with Brett Randolph.
    - Brett Randolph, [at Fredericksburg], to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 11 July 1804. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Pittsville Post Office, [Essex County], 25 July 1804. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, at B[owling ] Green, [Caroline County], to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 14 August 1804. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County), 12 December 1804. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, [Essex County], 19 December 1804. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph, at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 24 January 1805. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 27 February 1805. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, [Essex County], 20 March 1805. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, [Essex County], 27 March 1805. (Folder 1)
      Address changed to "the Reeds."
    - Brett Randolph, at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's [Post Office], [Essex County], June 1805. (Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1810-1819., 7 items. (Folder 1-2)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, [District of] Columbia, 2 February 1810. (Folder 1)
    - Brett Randolph to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, [D. C.], 21 July 1813. (Folder 1)
    - Lucy Randolph, at The Gift, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 16 July 1815. (Folder 1)
      Postmarked Culpeper, Virginia.
    - Richard Randolph, at Alexandria, to his uncle, Robert Beverley, at Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, Virginia, 23 July 1815. (Folder 1)
    - William Robinson, at Haward, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, near Loyd's [Post Office], Essex County, 5 February 1817. (Folder 2)
      Postmarked Alexandria.
    - Brett Randolph, at Richmond, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, Essex [County], 10 December 1817. (Folder 2)
    - Brett Randolph, at Richmond, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's [Post Office], Essex County, Virginia, 19 December 1817. (Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1820-1829., 16 items. (Folder 2)
    - J. A. Carrington, at Richmond, to [ ? ], 24 October 1821. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Richmond, to Robert Beverley, at Fredericksburg, 24 October 1821. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Richmond, to Robert Beverley, at Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 12 December 1821. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Williamsburg, to Robert Beverley, at Norfolk, January 1823. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Richmond, to Robert Beverley, at Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, Virginia, 5 April 1823. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 24 April 1823. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Richmond, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 21 June 1823. (Folder 2)
      This letter includes a statement of the account of Robert Beverley with Thomas B. B. Baber, administrator of Col. William Saunders.
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Up and down, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, 31 October 1825. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 1 October 1826. (Folder 2)
    - V. Moreau Randolph, at Richmond, Virginia, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, D. C., 28 November 1826. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., Spotsylvania [County), to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 9 October 1827. (Folder 2)
    - Two letters written on the same page, October-November 1827. (Folder 2)
      Richard Randolph, Jr., at Culpeper, to Philip Harrison, at Fredericksburg. 19 October 1827.
      P[hilip] Harrison to [ ? ]. 4 November 1827.
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Culpeper, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 2 December 1827. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Culpeper, to Philip Harrison, at Fredericksburg, 23 December 1827. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 4 February 1828. (Folder 2)
      Postmarked Culpeper Court House, Virginia.
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 14 May 1828. (Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1829-1834., 8 items. (Folder 2)
    - Three letters written on the same page, January 1829 - April 1930. (Folder 2)
      John H. Peyton, at Staunton, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia. 16 January 1829.
      R[obert] Beverley, to William A[ugustine] Washington. 28 January 1830.
      William Augustine Washington to Robert Beverley. April 1830.
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., Fauquier County, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, 24 January 1831. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Culpeper, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, June 1831. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 22 December 1833. (Folder 2)
      Postmarked Stevensburg, [Culpeper County], Virginia.
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, Virginia, 30 June 1834. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 15 August 1834. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Fredericksburg, to Robert Beverley, at Blandfield, Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 7 October 1834. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., to Robert Beverley, at Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, 11 December 1834. (Folder 2)
      Postmarked Culpeper C. H.
  - Letters, n.d., 8 items. (Folder 2)
    - Robert Beverley to [ ? ], n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Robert Beverley to [ ? ], n.d., Copy. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, D. C., n.d., 2 letters. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Culpeper, to Robert Beverley, near Loyd's Post Office, Essex County, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., at Culpeper Court House, to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Richard Randolph, Jr., to William Beverley, at Georgetown, District of Columbia, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - A cover sheet of a letter addressed to Robert Beverley, at Georgetown, D. C., n.d. (Folder 2)
- Other Papers, 1821-1822., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  Receipts for money paid to Richard Randolph, Jr., administrator of Maria Beverley, by Robert Beverley, October 16, 1821 and January 12, 1822. 1 piece.